Guide to the Mulberry and Northwood Presbyterian Churches, Wilkinsburg, Pa. Records, 1882-1992 AIS.1992.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Mulberry and Northwood Presbyterian Churches, Wilkinsburg, Pa. Records
1882-1992
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Northwood Presbyterian Church (Wilkinsburg, Pa.)
Mulberry Presbyterian Church (Wilkinsburg, Pa.)
AIS.1992.10
15 microfilm_reels
Mulberry Presbyterian Church was formerly known as the Second United Presbyterian Church of Wilkinsburg, Pa., until May, 1968. In 1971, the Mulberry Presbyterian Church merged with the Northwood Presbyterian Church located at North Avenue and Wood Street in Wilkinsburg, Pa. Northwood Presbyterian Church was formerly known as the First United Presbyterian Church of Wilkinsburg. This collection includes the records for both churches and spans the years from 1882 to 1992. The collection consists primarily of church minutes from the Mulberry Presbyterian Church Boards. Additional materials include church registers and a few articles of memorabilia.
History
Mulberry Presbyterian Church was formerly known as the Second United Presbyterian Church of Wilkinsburg, Pa., until May, 1968. Three elders of the First Presbyterian of Wilkinsburg; Messrs. H.E. Carmack, W.F. Bremner and E.T. Jackson, applied to organize a new church in September, 1903. On October 27, 1903, the Second Presbyterian Church of Wilkinsburg was formally organized in Penn Hall. On October 31, 1903 in Penn Hall, Rev. David R. Breed, D.D. conducted the first preaching service. Rev. George W. Mead became the first regular pastor on February 14, 1906. Originally, the church was built in three units: chapel, auditorium (1911), and main church (1912). On September 15, 1929, an education building was added. The Mulberry Presbyterian Church merged with Northwood Presbyterian Church in 1971.
Northwood Presbyterian Church was formerly known as the First United Presbyterian Church of Wilkinsburg, Pa. On November 21, 1882, the first service and organizational meeting of the First United Presbyterian Church occurred. The election of elders and trustees included: elders, T.D. Turner and Z.J. McIlvaine; trustees, John Bartley, William Turner, George McKee, Charles W. Hutchinson, W.S. Watt and James Porter. A lot was purchased at the corner of North Avenue and Wood Street for six hundred dollars. The church building was erected and finally dedicated in 1883. An auditorium was added in 1892, but this burned in 1895. A new building was constructed and then dedicated in 1896. The Northwood Presbyterian merged with Mulberry Presbyterian Church in 1971.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection includes the records for both the Mulberry Presbyterian Church and the Northwood Presbyterian Church. The records for the Mulberry Presbyterian Church span the years from 1903 to 1992 and are contained on reels 1 through 13. Reel 14 contains the records for the Northwood Presbyterian Church and covers the years from 1882 to 1971 at which time their records were incorporated into the Mulberry Church records.
The church registers for the Mulberry Presbyterian Church begin in 1903 and can be found on reel one. These registers include the roll of pastors, roll of elders, roll of deacons, roll of trustees, roll of communicants, baptisms, reserve roll, marriages, and deaths. The registers of church members for the Northwood Presbyterian Church for the years 1882 through 1971 are located at the beginning of reel 14.
The bulk of the collection consists of minutes from the Mulberry Presbyterian Church Board of Trustees (1908-1991), the Second Presbyterian Church Board of Session(1903-1968) and the Mulberry Presbyterian Church Board of Session(1968-1992). The minutes of the Board of Trustees from the date of the organization of the Church in 1903 to October 20, 1908 are reported lost. The collection also contains minutes of the Board of Deacons and Board of Session for the Northwood Presbyterian Church for the years 1959 to 1971.
Some articles of memorabilia are included for both the Mulberry Presbyterian Church (end of reel 13) and Northwood Presbyterian Church (end of reel 14).
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Western Pennsylvania Genealogical Society in 1992.
Existence and Location of Originals
Microfilmed by the Western Pennsylvania Genealogical Society, in cooperation with ais, from originals in the possession of Christ Episcopal Church, Ross Township, PA.
Previous Citation
Mulberry and Northwood Presbyterian Churches, Wilkinsburg, Pa. Records, 1882-1992, AIS.1992.10, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Mulberry Presbyterian Church, Wilkinsburg, PA, Records, 1905-1992, ais 92:10 Micro, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh and Northwood Presbyterian Church, Wilkinsburg, PA, Records, 1882-1971, ais 92:10 Micro Reel 14, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh.
Vital records (Document genre); Presbyterian Church -- Pennsylvania -- Wilkinsburg; Church buildings -- Pennsylvania -- Wilkinsburg; Wilkinsburg (Pa.) -- Church history; Wilkinsburg (Pa.) -- Genealogy; Church records and registers -- Pennsylvania -- Wilkinsburg; Death records; Baptismal records -- Pennsylvania -- Wilkinsburg; Marriage records; Churches and Synagogues; Church records; First United Presbyterian Church (Wilkinsburg, Pa.); Mulberry Presbyterian Church (Wilkinsburg, Pa.); Northwood Presbyterian Church (Wilkinsburg, Pa.); Second United Presbyterian Church (Wilkinsburg, Pa.)
- Church Registers, 1905-1992; I.
  - Volume 1, 1905-1927 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 1)
  - Volume 2, March 1927-May 1947 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 1)
  - Volume 3, June 1947-January 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 1)
  - Compilation of Registers (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 1)
  - Volume 4, June 1969-June 1992 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Record 1)
- Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1908-1991; II.
  - Volume 1, October 20, 1908 - November 1918 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 1)
  - Volume 2, December 12, 1918 - September 30, 1929 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 2-6)
  - Volume 3, October 20, 1929 - February 4, 1940 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 2-6)
  - Volume 4, February 4, 1940 - December 1947 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 2-6)
  - Volume 5, January 12, 1948 - December 17, 1952 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 2-6)
  - Volume 6, December 28, 1952 - January 20, 1957 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 2-6)
  - Volume 7, February 12, 1957 - June 8, 1960 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 2-6)
  - Volume 8, September 7, 1960 - April 5, 1964 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 2-6)
  - Volume 9, June 11, 1964 - November 12, 1970 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 2-6)
  - Volume 10, December 10, 1970 - November 8, 1978 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 2-6)
  - Volume 11, January 7, 1979 - December 12, 1991 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 2-6)
- Minutes of the Board of Session, 1903-1992; III.
  - Second Presbyterian Church, 1903-1968; 1.
    - Volume 1, October 28, 1903 - April 10, 1912 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 6-11)
    - Volume 2, April 14, 1912 - April 1, 1917 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 6-11)
    - Volume 3, April 8, 1917 - December 14, 1924 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 6-11)
    - Volume 4, January 5, 1925 - October 5, 1930 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 6-11)
    - Volume 5, October 6, 1930 - October 11, 1937 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 6-11)
    - Volume 6, November 8, 1937 - March 21, 1943 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 6-11)
    - Volume 7, April 18, 1943 - April 7, 1948 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 6-11)
    - Volume 8, May 5, 1948 - March 11, 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 6-11)
    - Volume 9, April 1, 1954 - May 8, 1958 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 6-11)
    - Volume 10, June 5, 1958 - November 7, 1963 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 6-11)
    - Volume 11, December 5, 1963 - May 19, 1968 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 6-11)
  - Mulberry Presbyterian Church, 1968-1992; 2.
    - Volume 12, June 6, 1968 - December 2, 1971 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 11-13)
    - Volume 13, January 1, 1972 - March 6, 1977 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 11-13)
    - Volume 14, April 20, 1977 - December 5, 1982 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 11-13)
    - Volume 15, January 19, 1983 - January 1, 1986 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 11-13)
    - Volume 16, January 21, 1987 - April 4, 1990 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 11-13)
    - Volume 17, April 18, 1990 - August 23, 1992 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 11-13)
- Memorabilia, IV.
  - Memorabilia, (13 articles) (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 13-14)
- Northwood Presbyterian Church, 1882-1971; V.
  - Registers of Church Members, Volumes 1-3, 1882-1971 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 14)
  - Minutes of Session, 1968-1971 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 14)
  - Minutes of the Board of Deacons, March 4, 1959 - October 10, 1971 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 14)
  - Memorabilia, (3 articles) (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Record 14)
- Mulberry Presbyterian Church, January 24, 1972 - February 25, 1979; VI.
  - Board of Deacons Minutes, January 24, 1972-February 25, 1979 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 6-7, Reel 15)